Guide to the Peter F. Dolan Photographs AIA.027
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Peter F. Dolan Photographs
1932-1989
1974-1989
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Dolan, Peter F.
AIA.027
1 Linear Feet in 1 record carton
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 5 series: Series I: Parades; Series II: Politics & Protests; Series III: Social Life; Series IV: People & Places; Series V: Photos by Other People. As the majority of the photos in the collection are dated, the materials within each series are arranged chronologically, as is the material within each folder. Any undated material appears at the back of the folder.
This collection is arranged into 5 series. As the majority of the photos in the collection are dated, the materials within each series are arranged chronologically, as is the material within each folder. Any undated material appears at the back of the folder.
Missing Title
Series I: Parades
Series II: Politics & Protests
Series III: Social Life
Series IV: People & Places
Series V: Photos by Other People
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Scope and Content Note
This collection consists of approximately 250 photographs, arranged in 5 series. The majority of the photos are black and white, 8 x 10 prints. While the collection also contains some photos that Dolan collected from earlier in the twentieth century, the majority of the photos were taken and printed by Dolan himself during the 1970s and 1980s, and focus heavily on Irish-American social and political events in and around New York City. The activities of many well-known Irish-American groups, such as the Ancient Order of Hibernians, The Friendly Sons of St. Patrick, the United Irish Counties Association (as well as individual county associations), and the Irish National Caucus are documented in the collection, along with images of the day-to-day life of individuals. As Dolan lived and worked in the Inwood neighborhood of Manhattan, many of the photos are focused there. There is also a heavy emphasis on Irish-American politics, particularly on protests about the political situation in Northern Ireland at the time.
Dolan provided handwritten descriptions of the majority of the photos in the collection. Most descriptions note the date, the event, and if known, identify the people in the photograph. Often, there are individuals indentified in these descriptive notes who are not mentioned in the folder titles. Although Dolan worked on a freelance basis, some of his photographs were published in Irish-American newspapers, and the description notes if the photograph was published.
Biographical Note
Peter F. Dolan (1942-2011) was an Irish-American photographer. Born in the Inwood neighborhood of Manhattan on November 8, 1942, he attended both Manhattan Prep and Manhattan College. Throughout his life, he worked to document the political and social life of Irish and Irish-Americans in New York City through photography. Although a freelance photographer, his work has appeared in such publications as the Irish Echo and the Irish Advocate. His photography studio and apartment were located in Inwood, and many of his photographs depict Irish life in that neighborhood. In addition to his photographic interests, Dolan was also interested in Irish music, particularly in the Irish tenor John McCormack. He was the secretary of the John McCormack Society of America, and donated his collection on John McCormack to the Boston College Library. He lived in New York City from birth through the 1990s, working at Keshkerrigan, a now-closed Irish-language book store on the Lower East Side, and in the office of Bronx Borough President Fernando Ferrer, and hosted Friday-night Irish music sessions in the Eagle Tavern (now closed) on 14th Street. Later in his life, he moved to Connecticut, and died in Hartford on January 2, 2011.
Custodial History Note
Peter Dolan transferred ownership and copyright of his photos to the New York Irish History Roundtable, who then donated the collection to the Archives of Irish America.
Parades |z New York (State) |z New York |v Pictorial works.; Peace movements |z Northern Ireland.; Irish Americans -- Ethnic identity.; Irish Americans -- Music.; Photographs.; Picketing |v Pictorial works.; Photographers |z New York (State) |z New York.; Photographic prints.; Session (seisun).; Irish Americans -- Social life and customs.; Irish Americans -- Societies, etc.; Irish Americans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Politics and government.; Irish Americans -- New York (N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Black-and-white photographs.; Saint Patrick's Day.; Irish Americans -- Politics and government.; Feis.; Demonstrations -- Pictorial works.; Color photographs.; Civil rights demonstrations |v Pictorial works.; Irish Americans.; Hunger strikes -- Northern Ireland.; Human rights |z Ireland.; Gaelic football.; Music festivals.; Irish -- Music.; Parades.; Inwood (New York, N.Y.) |x History |v Pictorial works.; Musicians |z New York (State) |z New York.; New York (N.Y.) -- Pictorial works.; Bronx (New York, N.Y.); Irish Northern Aid Committee; United Irish Counties Association of N.Y.; Irish Republican Clubs; O'Dwyer, Paul, 1907-1998; McAliskey, Bernadette Devlin, 1947-; New York St. Patrick's Day Parade Committee; Friendly Sons of St. Patrick; Gaelic Athletic Association; Emerald Societies. N.Y.; O'Brien, Nora Connolly; Ancient Order of Hibernians; Carey, Hugh
- Series I: Parades, 1977-1989
  Scope and Content Note
  The photos in these series are mostly group shots of parade committee meetings or groups marching in various parades. If the shots are with smaller groups of people, they are usually of the parade marshall or aides.
  - St. Patrick's Day Parade Committee Meetings, 1977-1985 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - St. Patrick's Day Parade, 1978-1985 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Rockaway Beach St. Patrick's Day Parade, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Brooklyn Irish American Parade, 1987-1989 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Series II: Politics & Protests, 1974-1989
  The photos in these series consist mainly of group shots at protests and picket lines in New York City. The majority of the people in the photos are not identified, although occassionaly there will be a shot of a more well-known speaker at a rally, like Paul O'Dwyer or Bernadette Devlin.
  - Stagg Commemorations, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Sargent Shriver with Washington Heights Sandhogs, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Anti-Carey Demonstrations, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Matilde Tone Commemoration, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Padraig Pearse Commemoration, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Irish Republican Club, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Hunger Strike Demonstrations, New York City, 1979-1983 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Irish National Caucus, 1979-1986 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - NORAID Demonstrations, 1979-1987 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Joe Doherty Demonstrations, 1980-1988 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - TWU Strike, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Protest against Prince of Wales Visit, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Irish Solidarity Day, 1981-1986 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Political Protests, 1981-1989 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Protest, Black Watch Regiment, Madison Square Garden, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Conferences, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Special Envoy to Northern Ireland, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Series III: Social Life, 1974-1988
  The photos in this series deal with special events in the Irish-American community in and around New York City. The majority of these are group shots of various social events. Individuals are identified in accompanying notes when known.
  - Cultural Events, 1974-1986 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Music Festival, Floyd Bennet Field, Brooklyn, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - New York County Association Events, 1975-1985 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Mt. Carmel Cemetery Restoration, 1976-1982 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Irish Freedom Show, 1977-1982 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Ancient Order of Hibernians, New York, 1977-1986 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Emerald Society of the Courts of New York, 1979-1985 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Religious Events, 1979-1988 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Mary from Dungloe Competition, Brooklyn, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - The Society of the Friendly Sons of St. Patrick, 1981-1986 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Gaelic Athletic Association (GAA) of New York Teams and Events, 1982-1984 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Kelly Games, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - United Irish Counties Association Events, 1983-1987 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - The Great Irish Fair, Coney Island, 1985-1987 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Series IV: People and Places, 1973-1987
  This series consists of close-up photographs of individuals or small groups, many of which taken in the Inwood neighborhood of Manhattan.
  - Portraits, 1973-1985 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Bernadette Devlin and Liam Kelly, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Inwood, Manhattan: Neighborhood Life, 1974-1986 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Eagle Tavern, 1975-1981 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - The Bronx, 1975-1982 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Liam O'Leary, 1978-1986 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Rockaway, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Musicians, Portraits, 1979-1987 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Nora Connolly O'Brien, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Series V: Photos by Other People, 1932-1981
  - Paul Delaney, Image of Great-Grandfather, unknown (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - 28th Annual UICA Irish Ball, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - John McCormack Archive Photos, [1930s] (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Kathleen Cooke Drawing & Sculpture, unknown (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Hunger Striker Patsy O'Hara, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Josephine Patricia Smith, unknown (Box 1, Folder 50)